<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cell Biology on Notesfinity</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/cell-biology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cell Biology on Notesfinity</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/cell-biology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Cell Membrane</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/cell-membrane/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/cell-membrane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-cell-membrane&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Cell Membrane&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The cell membrane, also known as the plasma membrane, is a crucial barrier that separates the interior of the cell from its external environment. It plays an essential role in maintaining cellular integrity, facilitating communication, and regulating the transport of substances. The composition, structure, and functions of the cell membrane are fundamental to understanding cellular processes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-composition-of-the-cell-membrane&#34;&gt;1. Composition of the Cell Membrane&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-phospholipid-bilayer&#34;&gt;a. Phospholipid Bilayer&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phospholipids:&lt;/strong&gt; The fundamental building blocks of the cell membrane are phospholipids, which consist of a hydrophilic (water-attracting) head and two hydrophobic (water-repelling) fatty acid tails. This amphipathic nature allows phospholipids to arrange themselves into a bilayer.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bilayer Structure:&lt;/strong&gt; The hydrophilic heads face outward toward the aqueous environments inside and outside the cell, while the hydrophobic tails face inward, away from water.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;b-membrane-proteins&#34;&gt;b. Membrane Proteins&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integral Proteins:&lt;/strong&gt; These proteins span the entire membrane and are involved in transport, acting as channels or carriers for molecules to pass through.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peripheral Proteins:&lt;/strong&gt; These are attached to the surface of the membrane and play roles in signaling and maintaining the cell’s shape.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;c-carbohydrates&#34;&gt;c. Carbohydrates&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Glycoproteins and Glycolipids:&lt;/strong&gt; Carbohydrates are often attached to proteins (glycoproteins) or lipids (glycolipids) on the extracellular surface of the membrane. They play crucial roles in cell recognition, signaling, and adhesion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;d-cholesterol&#34;&gt;d. Cholesterol&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Membrane Fluidity:&lt;/strong&gt; Cholesterol molecules are interspersed within the phospholipid bilayer. They help to stabilize membrane fluidity, making the membrane less permeable to very small water-soluble molecules that might otherwise pass freely through.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-structure-of-the-cell-membrane&#34;&gt;2. Structure of the Cell Membrane&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-fluid-mosaic-model&#34;&gt;a. Fluid Mosaic Model&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fluidity:&lt;/strong&gt; The cell membrane is often described by the fluid mosaic model, which illustrates the membrane as a flexible and dynamic structure. This model emphasizes that the lipid bilayer is not rigid; instead, it behaves like a fluid, allowing lipids and proteins to move laterally within the layer. This fluidity is vital for the proper functioning of the cell, as it enables the movement of proteins that are essential for various cellular processes, such as signal transduction and cell communication. Factors such as temperature and the types of fatty acids present in the membrane can affect its fluidity, with unsaturated fatty acids generally enhancing fluidity due to their kinked structures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Cell Wall</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/cell-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/cell-wall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-cell-wall&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Cell Wall&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The cell wall is a crucial feature of many organisms, including plants, fungi, and bacteria. It provides structural support, protection, and helps maintain the shape of the cell. The composition, structure, and functions of the cell wall vary significantly among different organisms, reflecting their unique ecological adaptations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-composition-of-the-cell-wall&#34;&gt;1. Composition of the Cell Wall&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-plant-cell-wall&#34;&gt;a. Plant Cell Wall&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Primary Component:&lt;/strong&gt; The main constituent of the plant cell wall is &lt;strong&gt;cellulose&lt;/strong&gt;, a polysaccharide made up of linear chains of glucose.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Components:&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hemicellulose:&lt;/strong&gt; A complex carbohydrate that interacts with cellulose to enhance structural integrity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pectin:&lt;/strong&gt; A polysaccharide that provides flexibility and helps bind cells together.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lignin:&lt;/strong&gt; Found in the secondary cell walls, it adds strength and rigidity, particularly in woody plants.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;b-fungal-cell-wall&#34;&gt;b. Fungal Cell Wall&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chitin:&lt;/strong&gt; The primary structural component of the fungal cell wall, chitin is a long-chain polymer of N-acetylglucosamine.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Components:&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Glucans:&lt;/strong&gt; Contribute to the overall structure and strength of the cell wall.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proteins:&lt;/strong&gt; Various structural and enzymatic proteins are integrated within the cell wall.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;c-bacterial-cell-wall&#34;&gt;c. Bacterial Cell Wall&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peptidoglycan:&lt;/strong&gt; The major component of bacterial cell walls, peptidoglycan consists of glycan chains cross-linked by short peptide bridges.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gram-Positive Bacteria:&lt;/strong&gt; Have a thick layer of peptidoglycan, often containing teichoic acids that contribute to wall stability.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gram-Negative Bacteria:&lt;/strong&gt; Have a thinner peptidoglycan layer and an outer membrane containing lipopolysaccharides, providing an additional barrier.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-structure-of-the-cell-wall&#34;&gt;2. Structure of the Cell Wall&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-plant-cell-wall-1&#34;&gt;a. Plant Cell Wall&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Primary Cell Wall:&lt;/strong&gt; A flexible and thin layer that surrounds the cell membrane. Composed of cellulose, hemicellulose, and pectin, allowing for cell growth.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secondary Cell Wall:&lt;/strong&gt; A thicker layer formed after the primary wall, rich in cellulose and lignin, providing additional support and rigidity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Middle Lamella:&lt;/strong&gt; A pectin-rich layer that cements adjacent cells together, facilitating cell-to-cell adhesion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/3f/Plant_cell_structure_svg_labels.svg/800px-Plant_cell_structure_svg_labels.svg.png&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Components of a Typical Plant Cell&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Components of a typical plant cell:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; a. Plasmodesmata&lt;br&gt; b. Plasma membrane&lt;br&gt; c. Cell wall&lt;br&gt; 1. Chloroplast&lt;br&gt; d. Thylakoid membrane&lt;br&gt; e. Starch grain&lt;br&gt; 2. Vacuole&lt;br&gt; f. Vacuole&lt;br&gt; g. Tonoplast&lt;br&gt; h. Mitochondrion&lt;br&gt; i. Peroxisome&lt;br&gt; j. Cytoplasm&lt;br&gt; k. Small membranous vesicles&lt;br&gt; l. Rough endoplasmic reticulum&lt;br&gt; 3. Nucleus&lt;br&gt; m. Nuclear pore&lt;br&gt; n. Nuclear envelope&lt;br&gt; o. Nucleolus&lt;br&gt; p. Ribosome&lt;br&gt; q. Smooth endoplasmic reticulum&lt;br&gt; r. Golgi vesicles&lt;br&gt; s. Golgi apparatus (Golgi body)&lt;br&gt; t. Cytoskeleton&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Chromosomes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/chromosomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/chromosomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-chromosomes&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Chromosomes&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chromosomes are thread-like structures located within the nucleus of eukaryotic cells and the cytoplasm of prokaryotic cells. They are composed of DNA and proteins and play a crucial role in the storage, transmission, and expression of genetic information. Understanding the composition and structure of chromosomes is vital for studying genetic inheritance and cellular processes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/2/2b/Chromosome_DNA_Gene.svg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Chromosome and DNA&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;A chromosome and its packaged long strand of DNA unraveled. The DNA&amp;rsquo;s base pairs encode genes, which provide functions. A human DNA can have up to 500 million base pairs with thousands of genes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Cilia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/cilia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/cilia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-cilia&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Cilia&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cilia are small, hair-like structures that extend from the surface of many eukaryotic cells. These structures play a vital role in cellular movement, fluid transport, and signal transduction. Cilia come in two primary forms: motile and non-motile (primary) cilia, each performing distinct functions in the cell.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/39/Bronchiolar_epithelium_3_-_SEM.jpg/800px-Bronchiolar_epithelium_3_-_SEM.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Bronchiolar Epithelium&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;SEM micrograph of motile cilia projecting from respiratory epithelium in the trachea.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-composition-of-cilia&#34;&gt;1. Composition of Cilia&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cilia are specialized organelles that play vital roles in movement and sensory functions in various cells. Their unique composition allows for their diverse functions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Endoplasmic Reticulum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/endoplasmic-reticulum/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/endoplasmic-reticulum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-endoplasmic-reticulum&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Endoplasmic Reticulum&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is a highly folded and complex membrane-bound organelle found in eukaryotic cells. It plays a critical role in the synthesis, folding, modification, and transport of proteins and lipids. The ER can be classified into two types: rough ER and smooth ER, each with distinct functions and structures.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-composition-of-endoplasmic-reticulum&#34;&gt;1. Composition of Endoplasmic Reticulum&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is a vital organelle in eukaryotic cells, playing crucial roles in protein and lipid synthesis, detoxification, and calcium storage. Its unique composition allows it to perform these diverse functions effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Golgi Bodies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/golgi-bodies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/golgi-bodies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-golgi-bodies&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Golgi Bodies&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Golgi bodies, also known as Golgi apparatus or Golgi complex, are essential organelles in eukaryotic cells involved in the modification, sorting, and packaging of proteins and lipids for secretion or delivery to other organelles. They play a crucial role in the post-translational modification of proteins and the formation of lysosomes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-composition-of-golgi-bodies&#34;&gt;1. Composition of Golgi Bodies&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Golgi apparatus, also known as the Golgi complex or Golgi bodies, plays a crucial role in the post-translational modification, sorting, and packaging of proteins and lipids for secretion or delivery to other organelles. Its unique structure and organization are essential for its functions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Lysosomes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/lysosomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/lysosomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-lysosomes&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Lysosomes&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lysosomes are membrane-bound organelles found in eukaryotic cells, often referred to as the cell&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;digestive system.&amp;rdquo; They contain a variety of hydrolytic enzymes that are critical for breaking down waste materials, cellular debris, and macromolecules. This process plays a vital role in maintaining cellular homeostasis and recycling components within the cell.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-composition-of-lysosomes&#34;&gt;1. Composition of Lysosomes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lysosomes are membrane-bound organelles that play a crucial role in the cellular degradation and recycling of macromolecules. Their unique composition is vital for their function in maintaining cellular homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Mitochondria</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/mitochondria/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/mitochondria/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-mitochondria&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Mitochondria&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mitochondria are membrane-bound organelles found in the cytoplasm of eukaryotic cells. Often referred to as the &amp;ldquo;powerhouses&amp;rdquo; of the cell, mitochondria play a central role in energy production by converting nutrients into ATP (adenosine triphosphate) through cellular respiration. Understanding the composition, structure, and functions of mitochondria is essential for grasping how cells generate and manage energy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-composition-of-mitochondria&#34;&gt;1. Composition of Mitochondria&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-outer-membrane&#34;&gt;a. Outer Membrane&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lipid Composition:&lt;/strong&gt; The outer membrane is composed of a phospholipid bilayer, similar to the cell membrane. It contains proteins that allow molecules to pass freely in and out of the mitochondrion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Porins:&lt;/strong&gt; Special proteins called porins make the outer membrane permeable to small molecules like ions, ATP, and ADP.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;b-inner-membrane&#34;&gt;b. Inner Membrane&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cristae:&lt;/strong&gt; The inner membrane is highly folded into structures called cristae, increasing the surface area for ATP production. This membrane is impermeable to most molecules, maintaining a specific environment for the reactions of the electron transport chain.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protein Complexes:&lt;/strong&gt; Embedded in the inner membrane are protein complexes essential for the electron transport chain and ATP synthesis.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;c-matrix&#34;&gt;c. Matrix&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enzymes:&lt;/strong&gt; The matrix, the innermost compartment of the mitochondrion, contains enzymes responsible for the Krebs cycle (citric acid cycle), which generates electron carriers for the electron transport chain.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA):&lt;/strong&gt; Mitochondria have their own circular DNA and ribosomes, allowing them to replicate and produce some of their own proteins independently of the nucleus.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-structure-of-mitochondria&#34;&gt;2. Structure of Mitochondria&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mitochondria are indispensable organelles found in nearly all eukaryotic cells, often referred to as the &amp;ldquo;powerhouses&amp;rdquo; of the cell due to their primary role in generating adenosine triphosphate (ATP) through oxidative phosphorylation. This vital function is facilitated by their intricate structure, which allows for the efficient conversion of biochemical energy derived from nutrients into ATP, the energy currency of the cell. Mitochondria exhibit a remarkable variety of shapes, including elongated, filamentous, and spherical forms, enabling them to adapt to the specific energy demands of different cell types. The mitochondrial structure comprises a double membrane organization, which creates five distinct regions that play critical roles in cellular metabolism:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Nucleus</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/nucleus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/nucleus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-nucleus&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Nucleus&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The nucleus is a membrane-bound organelle found in eukaryotic cells and serves as the control center, housing the cell&amp;rsquo;s genetic material. It is responsible for regulating cellular activities such as growth, metabolism, and reproduction by controlling gene expression. The nucleus plays a critical role in the storage and transmission of genetic information through DNA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6c/HeLa_cells_stained_with_Hoechst_33258.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;HeLa Cells&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;HeLa cells stained for nuclear DNA with the blue fluorescent Hoechst dye. The central and rightmost cells are in interphase, thus their entire nuclei are labeled. On the left, a cell is going through mitosis and its DNA has condensed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition, Structure, and Functions of Ribosomes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/ribosomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/eukaryotic/ribosomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;composition-structure-and-functions-of-ribosomes&#34;&gt;Composition, Structure, and Functions of Ribosomes&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ribosomes are essential macromolecular machines found in all living cells, responsible for synthesizing proteins by translating messenger RNA (mRNA) into polypeptide chains. They play a crucial role in the cellular machinery, linking amino acids together in the order specified by the genetic code.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-composition-of-ribosomes&#34;&gt;1. Composition of Ribosomes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ribosomes are essential cellular structures responsible for protein synthesis, composed of ribosomal RNA (rRNA) and ribosomal proteins. Their unique composition enables them to carry out the intricate process of translating mRNA into polypeptides.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concepts of Prokaryotic and Eukaryotic Cells</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/prokaryotic-eukaryotic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/prokaryotic-eukaryotic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;concepts-of-prokaryotic-and-eukaryotic-cells&#34;&gt;Concepts of Prokaryotic and Eukaryotic Cells&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cells are the fundamental units of life, and they can be classified into two main categories: prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells. Understanding the differences and similarities between these two cell types is essential for grasping the complexity of biological systems. This document outlines their key characteristics, functions, and implications in the study of life sciences.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview-of-prokaryotic-cells&#34;&gt;Overview of Prokaryotic Cells&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;definition&#34;&gt;Definition&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prokaryotic cells are simple, unicellular organisms characterized by the absence of a defined nucleus and membrane-bound organelles. They are typically smaller than eukaryotic cells, with diameters ranging from 0.1 to 5.0 micrometers. Prokaryotic cells represent one of the earliest forms of life on Earth, appearing around 3.5 billion years ago, and they play crucial roles in various ecosystems, including nutrient cycling, decomposition, and symbiotic relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction and Functions of Water</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/biomolecules-cell/water/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/biomolecules-cell/water/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction-and-functions-of-water&#34;&gt;Introduction and Functions of Water&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Water is a vital substance for all forms of life, making up a significant portion of living organisms. It is a unique molecule composed of two hydrogen atoms covalently bonded to one oxygen atom, giving it distinctive properties that make it essential for biological processes. Water serves as a solvent, a temperature regulator, and a participant in numerous biochemical reactions, playing a crucial role in maintaining homeostasis within organisms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction of Cells</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/introduction-of-cell/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/notes/neb/bio11/botany/cell/introduction-of-cell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction-of-cells&#34;&gt;Introduction of Cells&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cells are the fundamental units of life, serving as the building blocks for all living organisms. Each cell operates as an independent entity, carrying out various functions necessary for the survival and reproduction of the organism. Cells can be classified into two main types: prokaryotic and eukaryotic, which differ in structure and complexity. Understanding cells is essential for comprehending the basic principles of biology and the processes that sustain life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
